Welcome, everybody. I
am Dr. Patricia Koyman,
and I will be giving
the lecture today on
Short Leg Syndrome
and Heel Lift Therapy.
Here are the session
objectives. These are
also listed in your
class preparation guide.
What is short leg syndrome?
It is a misnomer, really.
The name is used due to
historical precedent. The
actual causes may be
unrelated to the leg lengths.
It is known as a
syndrome since there
are multiple symptoms
and findings.
There can be sacral
base unleveling. There
can be a compensatory
and omnic rotation.
And there can be caudal,
meaning lower lumbar, caudal
curve, side bending away
from the low sacral base.
That's most often the case,
but not always the case.
For diagnosis and treatment,
we want to treat all
somatic dysfunction diagnoses
as well as possible before
sending a patient for a
radiological evaluation.
Radiology, in terms of
measuring the coronal values
of iliac crests heights,
femoral head heights,
sacral base unleveling,
compensatory scoliotic
curves, the type, the
location, and the degree can be
performed. But remember,
with the radiological
evaluation, there could be
about 2 millimeters of human
error in measurement and
a 25% bony distortion.
So when we talk about
short leg syndrome and the
whole body compensation
related to that, we can
discuss the C scoliotic
response, which is shown
here in actually a reverse
letter C in this thoracolumbar
junction. We can see
the right shoulder
posterior view is higher
versus left shoulder lower.
In this example on the
right, the anominate
is rotating anteriorly,
and there's a pelvic
side shift to the left
side in this left view.
And then there's compensations
with the leg and the
foot happening as well.
On the other side here to
the right, we see there's
an S scoliotic response.
So a curve in the thoracic
spine to the right and
in the lumbar spine to
the left. So actually
it's a reverse letter S
in this posterior view. We
still have the right
shoulder higher relatively,
left shoulder lower, but
it's two different responses,
a C versus an S scoliotic
response in the vertebral
column. Pelvic side shift
in this case to the right is
to the right. And then there's
a compensatory anterior,
actually a nominate rotation
on the left side here.
And then also compensatory
rotations down
the chain as well.
So we can look at the
bony positions that
see scoliotic, S
scoliotic response. And
then we can look at
the ligaments involved.
Here we have the anterior
longitudinal ligament.
This is an anterior
view of the pelvic bowl.
We have the anterior
sacroiliac ligaments in
this region. We have
the iliolumbar ligament
anteriorly here. There's
also a posterior view
of the iliolumbar
ligament, posterior view.
And we also have the
posterior sacroiliac ligaments
in this region. There's
also the sacrospinous
ligament deep in here,
and here's the ischial
tuberosity and the
sacrotuberous ligament here,
very sick in this region.
So all of these with
compensations and rotations
of the anominates on
the sacrum could show
strain, and we'll look at
a slide soon over time,
can have calcifications.
This is a sagittal view,
so this is anterior here,
posterior view here,
so anterior-posterior
-sagittal view from the left
side of the vertebral
column. And going from
cephalad to caudad in
these bullet points is the
direction from anterior
to posterior of those
landmarks. So anterior
longitudinal ligament, ALL,
is here in the front along
the vertebral bodies.
Posterior longitudinal
ligament, PLL, is at the
posterior part of the vertebral
bodies deep inside here.
And we can see that also
from this posterior view.
Here is the posterior
longitudinal
ligament going down here.
Ligamentum flavum,
we can also see here
in this posterior
view most accurately.
Inter-spinous, as the
name sounds, inter-between
the spinous processes.
so this area between the
spinous processes are those
interspinous ligaments.
Supra again is the name sounds.
Supra is superior along
the top edge. So we
have supraspinous ligaments.
Intertransverse we
have in this area would
be here and then the
iliolumbar ligament we
have in this area here.
okay now in this slide we
have the iliolumbar ligament
labeled as one for the more
anterior portion and when
the anominate is showing
the rotational direction
forward this way there's
going to be the most strain
on this portion of the
anominate that labeled of the
iliolumbar ligament from that
anominate anterior rotation
versus if there's number
two a posterior rotation
that will put more strain on
this part of the ilialumbar
ligament labeled as two
and we see also in this
view this is an anterior view
below here and we see number
one these fibers would be
strained with an anterior
anominate strain and these
other fibers labeled two
which are more posterior,
they would be strained more
so with a posterior rotation.
In this radiological
view here, labeled letter
B, we can see that there's
areas of calcification going
on in that ligament, actually
a little bit on both
sides, but especially here.
And so functional can
turn into more structural
changes over a long
period of time in
terms of the calcifications
we see there.
back to the ilio lumbar
ligament in terms of a pain
pattern and a referral
from an asymmetry such as a
short leg syndrome and
postural imbalance here we note
that the ilio lumbar
ligament is stressed okay so
there is more stress being
put on that ligament in this
region so there can be a
referred pain pattern in
the area shown by this
shaded in region okay kind of
the if it's on this left
side, left lumbosacral region
into the lateral gluteal
region down the lateral
part of the thigh. This can
even go into the groin region
on that side. If it's a
male with our patient with
testicles, the pain can go
to the testicles. If it's
a patient with *****, the
pain could go to the *****
even. So a differential
diagnosis for pain could
be a referral pattern from
that ileo-lumbar ligament.
Moving on from
bones to ligaments,
we just looked at
now to muscles.
So here we have from the
clinically oriented anatomy
text, the colorful
images. This is a sagittal
view of the muscles of the
hip region. And we have
the color coding here.
If you go down flexors,
AD adductors, lateral
rotators, extensors, abductors,
medial rotators. You
can go through the color
coding here and see in
this wheel schematic
also where are the poles
of the muscles. Okay,
flexors coming up and in,
extensors in the yellow,
backwards,
lateral rotators, AD
adductors going medially, etc.
And it's showing the
arrows in the differential
pole of the muscles. So
as you're evaluating your
patient, Keep in mind what
are all the various muscles,
what are their mechanisms
of action, and how can
we help our patient maybe
with some strengthening
for weaker muscles and
some stretching for muscles
that are more tense,
inappropriately tense, so
that we can help them have
a better balance overall.
Okay, this slide is showing
a sagittal view. So let's
define our directions. A,
anterior, P, posterior.
So this is a view from the
right side of a patient,
schematic view. This would
be the vertebral column. So
this is S superior. Of
course, this is I inferior.
So we have the vertebral
column with the spinal
extensors attached posteriorly
here. And then the iliopsoas
and rectus femoris on
the enominate, especially
iliopsoas, is attaching to
the vertebral column. So in
terms of the vertebral
column, the balance front
anterior to back posterior
would be spinal extensors
posteriorly kind of pulling
up versus the iliopsoas
rectus femoris somewhat
pulling inferiorly. So there's
like a superior to inferior
differential pull there.
Now when we look at the, not
the vertebral column, but
now we move down to the
anominate, and we see what's
attached to the anominate
at the ischial tuberosity,
hamstrings, so that an
inferior pull there, and then
on the anominate, attaching
anteriorly, the abdominal
muscles with an upward
pull there. So in terms of
anominate, it's hamstrings
inferiorly versus abdominals
superiorly. okay and here
we have another um view of
the iliopsoas so um so as
major muscle there's also a
very small so as minor
muscle here along that
iliopectinial eminence but the
so as majors this larger muscle
attaching down here to the
lesser trochanter right
in here so and there are
special tests to evaluate
that. You will either learn
or you have learned the
Thomas test. That's an important
one to keep in mind that
you could perform on your
patient to see if there's
iliopsoas muscle hypertonicity.
Okay, so here's a
posterior view. Some of the
other muscles that could
be tight or weak, so they
may need stretching. They
may need strengthening.
a muscle we often consider
in terms of the posterior
gluteal region is this
piriformis muscle located
right in here coming
from the anterior lateral
edge of the sacrum over
to the posterior superior
portion of that greater
trochanter of the femur.
So again, here we have
piriformis muscle right in
here, very close to the
sciatic nerve. Sometimes
there can be some irritation
or some anomalous placement
of that nerve through
the piriformis muscle.
Also, things to keep in mind.
We talked about the hamstrings.
So here's some of
the hamstring muscles
here attaching to that
ischial tuberosity.
Okay, so for short leg
syndrome, we want to
evaluate the patient, get
some of their history.
What's going on? When
did their complaints
start? Is this something
new? Did it start
acutely? Has this been
going on for a while?
Is it chronic? What
is your patient's age?
finding out the
location of their pain
and the timing,
and a review of the
medications that the
patient is taking.
What are you going to
do for your examination?
Observe your patient
standing. Observe
their gait. How
are they moving?
And check for any leg length
discrepancy clinically.
Check for their range of
motion, always active and
passive range of motion.
Sometimes we abbreviate that
R-O-M, range of motion. and
checking active first before
passive because active is
what the patient can do
themselves and then passively
can you the physician
move them slightly more than
in their active range of
motion so sometimes in your
note abbreviation may be
a r o m a rom or p r o m
and that would be passive
range of motion and then
checking their muscle strength
with resistance so active
range of motion passive
and then muscle strength of
course a neurologic examination
upper and lower extremities
special tests as
needed we did mention the
thomas test before that would
begin before the psoas muscle
hypertonicity and there
may be other special tests
and we can we're going
to discuss some of them and
of course your osteopathic
structural examination in
all of ways that you know
and have learned to assess
or that you will learn to
assess the various parts
of the body so in terms of
standing posture we can go
from head head to toe or
some from cephalad to
caudad we have the occipital
region shoulder heights
comparing side to side is one
higher lower are they equal
the inferior angle of the
scapulas the iliac crest or
the waist creased region.
Okay, the PSISs,
sometimes we utilize that
standing flexion test.
If they're sitting, of
course, we would call it
the seated flexion test.
Laterally, sometimes
checking the height
of the greater trochanter
can be helpful.
Here's observing the
patient's stance again.
this picture from behind
the doctor is checking the
iliac crest heights level
and then ASIS and PSIS
level comparing side to
side does a patient have any
increased lordosis of the
lumbar spine and how is
the orientation of their
feet are their toes pointing
forward are they pointing
to the side is one
pointing to the side more
than the other side just
things to observe as you're
looking at their posture.
In terms of anterior
landmarks, again, you can
check iliac crest height.
Here's ASIS heights.
Usually we would use just
our thumbs perched on
the superior pubic
tubercle in this region.
And then here's checking
the medial malleoli with
your thumbs underneath
each medial malleolus.
Okay, for leg length
discrepancy, this comes from
Hoppenfeld, and there can be
an apparent discrepancy or
a true discrepancy. Hoppenfeld
discusses how one could
measure from the ASIS to
the medial malleolus, so one
fixed point to another
fixed point, and comparing
sites. So that is a clinical
option that one could use.
And in terms of comparing
femurs and tibias, patient
would be lying on their
back. So this is a bird's eye
view, so a patient lying on
their back. Now the patient's
bending their knees,
okay? If you look from the
feet towards their head and
you're comparing in this
letter A, each tibia, you
would check the tibial height.
Here we see that the right
tibia, in this case, looks
higher than the left
tibia. So we're clinically
observing in that situation
a tibial height differential.
Whereas if you go to the side
of the patient, better be,
and you look to
see what's going on
with the femoral
bones, the femurs,
in this case there's an
example of we're looking from
the right side of the
patient. So this being the
right femur does not extend
as far as the left femur.
Left femur here is
projecting more so than the
right femur, which is
ending about right there.
So in terms of a clinically
observed differential
of letter A, the tibias,
and letter B, the
femurs, This is a starting
point for figuring
out what pattern is
going on in your patient.
Okay, so other things you
can do is some special tests.
Some of these you
may have learned
already. Some you will
learn in the future.
Okay, and I highlighted here
the main ones that we'll
talk about right now.
these are ones you may have
done in your doctor-patient
relation course or you
will do in your doctor-patient
relation course so those
are good to know and keep
in your differential the
Adams forward bend test
and that's something that
we often do when we have
a patient with a suspected
scoliosis we can also do
it if we're suspecting any
kind of asymmetry maybe it's
not a full-fledged scoliosis,
but maybe it's a type
1 group curve where we
could still see a slight rib
hump, maybe not as prominent
as in a scoliosis where
we may have used a
scoliometer to get an initial
degree measurement on that.
So that's something one
could check as well. And
then the hip drop test,
we'll go over that, and
that is to assess lumbar
involvement. The name does
have the word hip, but
it's not technically for
the hip joint per se. It's
really that, and we'll
go over this, that the hip
or the so-called innominate
is dropping down and
that the point of the
special test is to assess
that lumbar involvement.
So here we'll go over that.
This is in your DG Ivana
text, fourth edition. If
you want to take a look
at that, you can click on
this link, But here's the
patient standing, facing
away from the practitioner.
The so-called hip drop
test, as noted here,
is also known as
lateral lumbar flexion.
Lateral flexion is another
name for side bending. So
we're talking about the
lumbar spine side bending for
the hip drop test. So they
stand away from you, and
all of these steps are
describing what is the patient
doing. They're standing
with their feet comfortably
apart, about four to six
inches, feet flat on the floor.
And the patient is bending
one knee at a time. As
the patient bends this right
knee, then her iliac crest
or an omelet on that side
is dropping lower than the
other side. And then we
compare, ask the patient to
straighten that knee and
bend the other knee. And then
we compare, does the patient
equally bend and have a
drop in their iliac crest in
approximately equal amount
of degrees on the right
side versus the left side?
This would be, when things
are even, that would
be your zero degrees. And
then depending how much
they drop, here would be
your angle of measurement.
And you would eyeball
it in terms of comparing
to the other side. Is it
equal or is it unequal?
The side, and
this is where it's
describing here, what
your findings mean.
If a patient actually has
a group curve in their
spine, they may be able to
more easily drop their hip
or their iliac grasp at a
moment on the side that's
opposite to their natural
side bending position that
they're in. If they have a
straight spine and no pre
-existing curve in their
lumbar region, then they may
be more even in their dropping
okay this is describing
um let me go back here
so this was from DG Ivana
here's a link of myself
doing a video describing with
this blue flexible ruler
this hip drop test against
similar instructions as
the DG Ivana resource so
take a moment to get familiar
with this hip drop test
and what it means in terms
of the lumbar involvement
that the patient may be
having. Yes, no, maybe. Do
they have a preexisting
group curve in that region?
Adams forward bend test.
Again, this is often
done with the patient
feet either together or
slightly apart, bending
forward, looking at eye level,
comparing one side to the
other in their thoracic
cage or rib cage region.
And do you see a rib
hump in that region?
That would indicate some
rotational component
of that thoracic spine,
causing the ribs to be more
posterior on that side.
Some sample findings.
And then once they bend
forward, then the patient
could swing their arms
to one side and then
to the other side. And
then you see when they
side bend towards the
side of the rib hump, does
it go away or not? That
can give you information
about whether the curve
is more functional.
if it disappears, or
if it's more structural
in nature. So you're
information gathering,
you're being an
osteopathic detective,
trying to figure
these things out.
Okay, so moving
on from bones to
ligaments to muscles
to special tests.
Sacral-based unleveling,
x-rays. So maybe
you send your patient
for some x-rays.
Here with letter A,
we have a view of
the coronal view.
And then in letter
A, coronal, letter
B is sagittal view.
So here we can see this
line is the most important
this way, matching the
sacral base. And we can
see that it does have
an unleveling, so lower,
higher. And we can see
that this patient actually
had a hip replacement. So
there's a hip prosthesis
in place here that may
have contributed to maybe
a new differential in the
leg lengths. Maybe the
patient originally had a
leg length differential.
We would need more of a
history to know about that.
But if we wanted to work
with the patient, if
this asymmetry was giving
them pain on up into their
back, maybe we could
lift, put a heel lift on
the one side. So we're,
again, information gathering.
There's also angles
here. here it looks like
it's marked 43 degrees
like what does this mean in
terms of any lumbosacral
pain here we have lumbar
spine the sacrum itself
so this would be anterior
this would be posterior
so checking those things
here's a graphic from
the third edition of the
foundations of osteopathic
medicine where we have a stick
figure key here they had
looked at many patients it
looks like 738 patients
in terms of a leg length
difference the stick figure
imaging showing the lumbar
spine on the triangle image
sacrum these arcing arcs
to the side the anominates
or iliac crest the iliac
crest of the anominates
the round ball the femoral
head and then the femur as
the stick legs of the stick
going down so what are
the various shapes and
orientations that they found
in terms of the percent of
the group so that's the
percentage here of frequency
the less frequent is farther
over to the right where
these there's these smaller
bar graphs so we see that
more often in the more
prevalent findings we have
on the short leg side here
this very first bar graph
here showing a shorter
right is posterior view leg
and showing the sacral base
unleveling towards right
lower on the right and then
the lumbar spine doing a
caudal curve side bending
away so side bending to the
left when there was a right
short leg and then if it
was a left short leg the
exact opposite side bending
to the right so there's a
convexity on the left and
a concavity on the right
and that those were the more
typical findings but when
you're evaluating your
patients and figuring out what's
going on And it's important
to know that your patient
may have findings that
aren't the most typical.
Okay, so example, there's
fewer in this part of the
bar graph, the next group
over. There's really not a
curve happening in the lumbar
spine. It's really just
straight. So this patient,
again, same configuration of
the right short leg, right
short leg. But instead of
actually side bending and
compensating side bending
away from the short leg,
They're kind of tipping
into it even further. This
situation may lead to even
more discomfort or pain in the
patient's body, in their
back, in their spine, all
these muscles and ligaments.
They have to work really
hard on this left side to
kind of keep them upright.
Same thing for the opposite,
you know, left short leg
here, but the same thing.
They're not compensating
with a spinal curvature away
to kind of get a little more
balance. They're really
going up and out to the left.
And then in this opposite
scenario here, then all
of these right-sided muscles
would be aggravated and
working much harder for the
patient, maybe leading them
to have more pain. And
then as we go from left to
right, there are all these
other permutations with the
leg length difference that
could be seen in a patient.
That bar graph image
was from the third
edition. Next slide.
This is from the fourth
edition, where they have
a nice pie graph showing
the frequency distribution.
And we can see
the blue letter A and
the orange letter B.
That corresponded
to the prior bar
graph with these
higher percentages.
So what they're labeling
is 1 and 1B being the most
prevalent. And they're also
noting here with an asterisk
where the lumbar spine is
straight. so that happened
in a couple of these
recorded findings and we have
the letter I think it's
letter C it gets a double
asterisk and they're saying
that's an atypical lumbar
response here's another double
asterisk the letter F here
atypical lumbar response
in letter F so keeping in
mind that atypical responses
may lead to increased pain
syndromes for the patient.
So it's just good to know
that it's not so cookie
-cutter defined that it's
always going to be A or B
only, even though they are the
most prevalent responses
that the patient may have.
Keep in mind that there can
be these atypical responses
as you're doing your
detective work. So how can
we help the patient who
has a short leg syndrome?
and we can incorporate
heel lift therapy
with osteopathic
treatment. So what do we do
first? Do OMT first. And
then as you've released
some of the areas that
are the most restricted
and areas of discomfort
for the patient, they
may be in a better
musculoskeletal orientation.
Maybe you've sent them
off for some postural x
-rays. But what are we
going to do in terms of
the heel lift therapy?
we're going to add the
heel lift to the side of
a lowered sacral base.
So that's the key point here.
We want to add it to the
side of the lowered sacral
base. And then this is also
very important that we
acknowledge in this process
of adding the heel lift to
their shoe and doing the
osteopathic treatment that this
is a slow process of postural
realignment and re-education
that they're going to
experience throughout their
whole body. So taking the
time that one needs to help
the patient to get this
new physical understanding
that they're going to have.
Here's a nice quote. Heel
lift treatment using the
osteopathic postural model
is always combined with OMT.
So it's not just give them
a heel lift and they're off
on their way. It's a
process using our hands-on
treatment as well as providing
them with the heel lift
therapy. So what do the heel
lifts look like? There's
many different types of heel
lifts that can be ordered.
Here in the upper left
corner, this is a purely cork
heel lift. Here's a little
bit of a fancier cork heel
lift where they've put leather
on top for a little bit
more durability of the device.
here on the left there's
some rubber heel lifts
you can see red blue black
different thicknesses okay
depending on what you need
and we're going to go
over the formulas for the
thicknesses here in the middle
there's the clearly adjustable
heel lift you can see there's
layers it's the longest
layers on the top everything's
very flat here and
on the underneath there's
progressively shorter heel
lifts as one goes posteriorly.
Each layer is about a
millimeter thick. I believe
this has 12 layers approximately
so this would be 1.2
centimeters measurement from
the hole in the the hole
height from the back and
then over here we have a blue
foam heel lift. If you have
some kind of foam material
it does need to be firm
if it's not firm it's usually
not as advisable because
it could just over time get
too too worn down for the
patient to be able to maintain
the amount of lift that
they need so something
more firm like this more
plastic material the cork
rubber the cork with leather on
it would be preferable so
those are the choices and
what they look like of heel
lifts again available for
patients to purchase and it
would guide them on that.
So what is the formula that
we're going to be using?
This is from David Heidlich,
a D-O-F-A-A-O, and he
came up with a formula that
could be used to figure out
what is the initial heel
lift height that a patient
could utilize for their short
leg syndrome. So this is
something that you would
want to memorize and know
how to plug in the numbers.
So there's L is for lift,
okay the lift required l
that's the first thing here
will be less than or
equal to less than because
you may start much much
at a much lower level than
the final number from the
formula so that you build
up to that final number that
you get from this formula
and sbu sacral base on
leveling and that would
be the number that's
determined by the radiological
evaluation we're We're
going to do four examples
using the same number for
the sacral base unleveling.
And we're going to say
it's half an inch for
the following examples
that we're going to do.
And this is divided by
D plus C as a unit. And
what is D? D is duration
plus compensation.
So duration has three choices
of a number attribution.
one, two, or three.
The letter D, you can see,
has a straight component
and then the round component.
So to help you remember
that it's one, two, and
three, D has this straight
component like the number
one. So the three choices for
duration start with number
one, okay, because it's
straight there, one, two,
three. What does one represent?
That's going to represent
0 to 10 years of duration.
Now, in your assigned reading,
number two is technically
given the duration of 10
to 30 years, and number
three is given 30 and more
years. There's a little bit
of overlap between the numbers
10 and 30, so to decrease
confusion, any test
questions you may encounter,
level two, the number two,
will be kind of sandwiched
in there and involve only
the years 11 to 29 years.
To be fair and consistent
with 1, anything 0 to 10,
2, 11 to 29,
3, 30 years and beyond
for the duration.
Now that leaves one more letter
here, C, compensation.
What is C for?
There's three numbers, 0,
1, 2. The letter C, as you
can see, is rounded. If
we were to keep going and
close it we would have a
zero so that's how you know
compensation begins with
zero so zero means there's no
compensation observed one
means there's some side
bending and especially
the compensatory rotation
associated with their vertebral
segments and two the highest
amount of compensation
there's the wedging the
set size changes and plates
with horizontal growth
spurring and so many of the
degenerative changes show up
for the patient. You would
give that a value of 2.
So now we're going to do
four examples, put this all
together for you. We're
going to, again, keep it
simple by using half an
inch as the sacral base
unleveling that we received
from a radiologist's report.
So case number
one, a patient has
healed from a right
femoral fracture.
The right femur is now
longer than the left femur.
And he has a one-half inch
sacral base unleveling.
And the new asymmetry
is of minimal duration.
And the patient has no
compensatory changes.
Okay.
And using the Heilig
formula, how much heel lift
would you provide? And
on which side? And these
are all the choices
here. So we're going to
plug in the numbers to
the Hilick formula. So the
amount of lift is equal
to the sacral base
unleveling divided by
duration plus compensation.
So sacral base
unleveling is the
one-half inch
divided by duration.
We attribute a value of
one because it's a very
short duration, certainly
less than 10 years,
plus, and we said there
was no compensation at all.
So that gives a C
compensation value of zero.
So a half divided by
basically one is a half.
Okay, and we know that
it was a fracture and the
patient healed with the
right femur longer. So with
short leg syndrome, we want
to put the heel lift on the
shorter side. So that's
going to be the left side.
So a half-inch heel lift
on the left side, the
shorter leg side, would
be the correct answer.
Let's do another example.
Again, here's our key
that we are working with
so that you are becoming
familiar and memorizing
this formula and that you
feel comfortable plugging
in the numbers here.
Here we go.
Case number two. So
now the patient is
35 years old and
had a right lower
extremity injury in
early youth at age 10,
which led to his one-half
inch right lower sacral
basal leveling. He has
minimal compensation
with side bending and
rotation changes noted.
Using the Hilick formula,
how much of a heel lift and
on which side would you
prescribe for this patient?
Okay, so we're going
to plug in the numbers.
So we have the amount
of lift, that's
what we're trying
to figure out,
equals the sacral base
unleveling. We still have
that half an inch divided
by duration. And we're going
to give the duration a
number 2. Why are we doing
that? Because it happened
when the patient's 35.
The patient's 35 now happened,
the injury happened when
they were age 10. So 35
minus 10 is 25 years. So
duration, 25 years fits right
in the middle of this number
2 for duration. So we're
going to give duration a 2.
And then the case is describing
compensation with side
bending and rotation changes.
And we note that that
gets a value of 1, which
we have right here. So 2
plus 1 is 3. So we have a
half divided by 3, which is
the same as 1 half times 1
third equals 1 sixth. and
we know that the lower
sacral base was on the right
side, a right lower sacral
base. So we would want to
say that the correct answer
is one-sixth inch heel
lift placed on the right
side, so in the right shoe.
And that would be
the correct answer.
Okay, let's do a couple more.
Again, here's our reference
point, memorizing this and
having everyone feel
comfortable with working out any
formulas. So case number
three. In this case, we have
a 75-year-old patient who
had an injury in his youth
at age 15 that led to his
current one-half inch left
lower sacral base unleveling.
He has lumbar vertebral
end plates with horizontal
growths and spurring marked
rotation. How much of a heel
lift would you prescribe
and on which side? so
remember we're looking at all
the findings so we have
again we want to figure out
the amount of lift needed
sacral base unleveling divided
by duration plus compensation
so we have the same
for our examples half inch
sacral base unleveling divided
by duration we got a three
how did we get a three
duration he's 75 years old
happened when he was 15 75
minus 15 leaves 60 60 years.
So that duration definitely
falls within this category
3. It's 30 or more years.
So 60 years. So we definitely
get a 3 for duration.
Compensation. How do we
get a number 2 with all
the findings that we have
here? The horizontal growth,
the spurring, the
rotation. We can see that
here. That goes with a
compensation assigned value
of 2. So we have 3 plus 2
is the 5. So 1 half inch
divided by five or that's
the same as one-half
times one-fifth and then
we get one tenth and which
side does this go on we
said that the left lower
sacral base was unlevel
so we're going to say we
want one tenth inch on
the left side for the heel
lift therapy all right
we'll do one more here's our
formula you need to memorize
and be able to work with
comfortably with all of
these parameters so here
we go case number four this
time it's a 26 year old
patient who had polio which
affected her right leg in
her youth at age 12 she
has a half inch right lower
sacral base on leveling
and no compensatory changes
how much of a heel lift
would you prescribe and on
which side So we're going
to fill in the parameters
here. Again, we want to
know how much lift. Sacral
base unleveling divided by
duration plus compensation.
We have our half an inch
divided by duration. We
got a 2. How did we get a
2? So she's 26 years old.
She had the polio
affecting her at age 12. So
26 minus 12. And we get
into 14 years. It's been
going on. So 14 years
fits into that duration
number of 2. So that's
where we put in a 2 here.
The other attribution
is compensation.
It says no compensatory
changes. If there's none
observed, that gets a 0
for compensation, which
we have right there. 2
plus 0 is 2. So 1 half for
the sacral base in Loving
divided by 2 here is
the same as 1 half times
1 half equals 1 quarter.
And which side, we said it
was a right lower sacral
base, so we're going to put
that quarter inch on the right
side. so we have right
side we have a quarter inch
heel lift that we're going
to prescribe on that site
okay so that this is what
you need to know and we just
did four examples take some
time to review those as you
need to so that David Heilig's
formula is comfortable
for you okay so overall
for your diagnosis in your
evaluation before adding the
lift check other things is
a short leg due to something
going on in the feet? Do
they have foot pronation?
Do they need to have some
orthotics made specifically
for them? See a podiatrist and
do they need a heel lift
as well? Sometimes the
orthotic device or insert into
their shoe could also have
a little bit of a lift placed
on it. So these are things
to consider as well. What's
going on in the pelvis?
Is there a rotation or an
up shear or a down shear?
So treat osteopathically.
We mentioned that earlier.
Treat osteopathically first,
often before you even maybe
send them for a postural
study, and then considering
the heel lift therapy. Is
the short leg due to short
leg syndrome? Remember, it
is a syndrome that could
be due to potentially an
actual short leg, or it could
be that there's the
compensatory changes coming from
the enominate itself and
any other postural changes.
So we're what's going on
with the patient. Things
to look for after you've
treated and put in the
proper heel lift or
you're working up to the
proper heel lift, check
the standing flexion test.
That should become negative
once the proper heel
lift has been put in
place and the patient has
no more pelvic or lower
extremity dysfunctions.
In terms of how much heel
lift can go where in relation
to the foot and the shoe
and the heel, the maximum
heel lift inside a shoe
would be one quarter an inch
higher than that it just
feels uncomfortable and their
patient's foot and heel may
kind of slip out of their
shoe and then in terms of
the maximum amount between
the the patient's heel and
the floor that would be a
half an inch and then we're
going to go over this but
variable placement of the
lift materials is possible so
in this picture this is
where we we see the variable
placement of the lift material
and letter a this is a
side view uh let's say from
the uh from the right side
looking towards the left
so uh the patient here's
their shoe the heel of their
shoe we can see the bony
drawing of the the laterally
here this is the right foot
so the fibula here and the
tibia on the other side
we see the calcaneus we see
the here the metatarsals and
the phalanges here. So this
is without a heel lift.
Letter B,
okay, we see this
speckled area right under
here. That's the heel
lift inside the shoe,
and that's a maximum
of a quarter inch.
Letter C here, we have two
materials, not only the lift
inside the shoe here, but
a little bit on the outside
of the shoe as well. And
the maximum in this scenario
would be a quarter inch
inside the shoe and another
quarter inch on the heel of
the shoe and that adds up
to the one half inch maximum
between this the calcaneus
bone here in the middle of
the bone to the bottom of
the shoe so that's the maximum
half an inch now if the
patient needs more than
half an inch of a lift you
would lift them to this half
an inch initially and then
any amount that you add on
After that half an inch that
you add just posteriorly,
you would add both to the
anterior, which you can see
right here, anterior portion
of the shoe, and to the
posterior part of the shoe.
So letter D is a little
bit tricky because it's
showing not only what B and
C have, the quarter inch
inside the shoe, and
the quarter inch on the
outside. but let's say they
needed another one-eighth
of an inch it would be
added in addition to both
to the front and the back
of that same side shoe
and this is this drawing
here is kind of explaining
the rationale for that
this one as well when
you add too much height
only to the heel beyond
the one-half inch then in
In the transverse plane,
the whole pelvic bowl
will rotate too much
to the side away from
the heel lift side.
So beyond half an inch,
what you need to do to
derotate that pelvic bowl
back to the symmetry of the
midline, that's where
you're going to add the heel
lift, sorry, the lift also
to the front part of the
foot. So you're derotating
any excessive rotation
beyond that initial half an
inch that you're lifting.
Okay, moving on.
So things to keep in mind.
When you add the heel lift,
the compressive forces
can cause a bone to grow
faster. Okay, so if you're
using this heel lift therapy
in a child, the lift under
the short leg may cause
that leg to grow faster.
Meaning, as they're growing,
they may actually even
out any slight leg length
differential that they may
have had. So, in that case,
you really want to monitor
carefully in children.
And this is what we
discussed in the prior slide
about adding a little bit
to the anterior part of
the foot because that will
affect pelvic rotation.
When you add the anterior
lift, it's going to
bring that pelvis to the
same side that you are
adding the anterior lift
to. and that prevents
the excessive rotation
away when you're adding
the lift posteriorly at
the level of the heel.
Okay, and finally
here, what's the
overall goal? We're
going to re-educate the
patient towards a
more ideal posture.
Treatment. Yes, we want to
include with our heel lift
osteopathic treatment, relaxing
and stretching muscles,
correct any somatic
dysfunctions, and increase the
patient's mobility. We can
give homework exercises,
either stretching
or toning would
be considered like
strengthening.
So as appropriate,
think muscles that are
weak, you would like
to tone. Muscles
that are tight, you
would like to stretch.
And then, of course, the
lift therapy that we've
been talking about, based on
the sacral base unleveling
and the length of time
present and the amount,
which is D duration,
you all may have this
formula memorized now, and
the amount of C compensation
and plugging that
all into the formula.
so what can correcting the
apparently short extremity
do we want to go more towards
this direction if this
is a plumb line plumb line
meaning the hanging line
from the ceiling comparing
right side to left side we
want to get more towards
equality okay with the heel
lift in place everything
lining up from the feet to
the hips to the pelvic bowl
and to the spine versus
if their patient is untreated
they have a discrepancy
they have all this asymmetry
pelvic side shifting
curves going one way and
the other way sometimes in a
way you may not expect so we
want to correct many other
postural defects they're
shifting their pelvis
shifting and realigning them
back getting their center of
gravity lined up okay just
to finish up our summary
is we had an introduction
to short leg syndrome and
to heel lift therapy incorporating
osteopathic treatment
and we consider the
potentially involved anatomical
areas bony ligament is
muscular and special tests
that you can do and as well
as becoming comfortable
with calculating the heel
lift height using David
Heilig's formula okay here
are references for you this is
your assigned reading if you
click on the links either
here or in the CPG. That
will be helpful for you.
And then here to the end
of the PowerPoint are
questions for your
review. There are about 13
review questions. Some
are just a couple are
just, you know, thought
provoking questions for
you to consider the
material and your reading.
And hopefully that's helpful
for you to consolidate
everything that you learned
in this introduction
to short leg syndrome and
heel lift therapy. Thank
you so much for your time.
I hope you learned a lot.
And please reach out if
anyone has any questions.
You can always email
me. Thank you so much.